Register of the Donald Marquand Dozer Papers
Hoover Institution Archives
- U.S. GOVERNMENT SERVICE FILE, 1937-1973
  - State Department
    - Division of Research for American Republics (DRA) (Transferred from the Office of American Republics Affairs to the Office of Intelligence Research in but its basic function remained unchanged), February 1947
      - Reports
        - Colombia. Unidentified holograph, short typescript reports, memoranda, and dispatch, 1942-1945 (Folder 18)
        - Cuba. Dispatches and telegram, 1945-1950 (Box 55, Folder 1)
        - Dutch West Indies (Curacao). Dispatch, 1949 (Folder 2)
        - Ecuador. Dispatch, 1949 (Folder 3)
        - Haiti. Dispatch, 1945 (Folder 4)
        - Honduras. Memorandum, 1949 (Folder 5)
        - Mexico. Memorandum, clippings, holograph, dispatches, speech transcript, 1943-1948 (Folder 6)
        - Nicaragua. Typescript draft, undated (Folder 7)
        - Panama. Memoranda and clippings, 1948 (Folder 8)
        - Paraguay. Memoranda, holograph drafts, typescript reports, relating primarily to the internal political situation, 1945-1948 (Folder 9)
        - Peru. Memorandum, dispatches and typescript report, 1945-1949 (Folder 10)
        - Uruguay
          - General, Letter, memorandum, typescript reports and unidentified holograph draft, 1949 (Folder 11)
          - Multilateral intervention initiative, Text of note from Alberto Rodriguez Larreta, news reports and analyses of Latin American reaction to the proposal., 1945 november-1946 March (Folder 12-13)
        - Venezuela. Memoranda, reports and dispatches, 1944-1950 (Folder 14)
    - Office of Public Affairs, Division of Historical Policy Research
      - General
        - General, Staff lists and descriptions, general memoranda, 1951-1954 (Folder 15)
        - Inter-American Information Committee, Notes, memoranda, minutes, 1952 (Folder 16)
      - Bibliographies
        - "Brief List of References on The Paris Peace Conference of " undated, 1919 (Folder 17)
        - "Current American Thinking on Democracy," (revised) Memoranda, drafts and mimeographed copy of final bibliography, 1951 september-october (Folder 18)
      - Reports and Projects
        - General. Summary and short reports (Folder 19)
        - "Conduct of Peace Negotiations during The War of 1812," Mimeographed report, 1946 december (Folder 20)
        - "The Problem of Recognition in American Foreign Policy," Mimeographed report, 1950 august (Folder 21)
        - Korean Assistance Program. Lists of offers from various countries, 1951 january-March (Folder 22)
        - "Russia and the Versailles Peace Conference," Notes, handwritten memorandum, report drafts, 1951 April-May. (Folder 23)
        - "Council of Europe," Memoranda, drafts of report, 1951 november-december (Folder 24)
        - "Toward Closer European Unity: Recent Official Organizations," Notes, memoranda with comments and proposed introductory section, typescript draft of report, 1951 december-1952 february (Folder 25)
        - United States Foreign Policy. Typescript drafts of short reports and outlines, memoranda, 1951-1952 (Folder 26)
        - McCarthy Project, Relates to efforts by the State Department to refute or respond to Senator McCarthy's criticisms of that department. Letter, press release, memoranda, and a report by Hornell Hart, "McCarthy Versus the State Department.", 1951-1957 (Folder 27)
        - "American Policy Toward China," Clippings, notes, memoranda, 1951-1952 (Folder 28)
        - "General Eisenhower's Campaign Statements on Foreign Policy," Typescript compilation and mimeographed source notes, circa 1952 (Folder 29)
        - "Political Relationships," Prepared for the Committee on Interstate and Foreign Commerce. Typescript draft, 1952 january 27 (Folder 30)
        - "Portugal and the West," Outline and holograph draft of report, memoranda and correspondence, 1952 january-July (Box 56, Folder 1)
        - Bi-National Cultural Centers, Typescript reports, memoranda, notes, 1952 november (Folder 2)
        - Point Four Project (Defense History Project), Guidelines, memoranda and typescript preliminary draft/outline, 1952 July-1953 october (Folder 3)
        - "Latin American Chiefs of State since 1930," Typescript with memoranda, 1953 august-september (Folder 4)
        - "The United States and Nicaragua: A Survey of Relations from " 1953 january-november Outline, typescript and holograph partial drafts, memoranda, notes. Includes galley proofs of a chapter entitled "Nicaragua" from an unidentified book, 1930-1953 (Folder 5)
- PANAMA CANAL FILE, 1901-1980
  Correspondence, reports, memoranda, clippings, newsletters, petitions, speech and hearing transcripts, press releases, pamphlets, flyers, treaty texts, notes, resolutions, serial issues and other miscellany. Arranged by subject (interest groups).
  - General
    - General
      - General
        - Non-printed material. Bibliographies, newsletter, book review, excerpt from Panama Canal transit log, address list, broadcast transcript, miscellany, 1968-1976 (Box 56, Folder 6)
        - Printed material
          - Clippings and serial articles, 1964-1980 (Folder 7-9)
          - Maps (Folder 10-12)
      - "The Case for a Sea-Level Isthmian Canal," Mimeographed copy, attributed to a Col. Sheffey., 1965 (Folder 13)
      - Commerce Department (Folder 14)
        - "General Population Characteristics: Canal Zone," Printed pamphlet, 1972 february
        - "Number of Inhabitants: Canal Zone," Printed pamphlet, 1971 november
      - John Frank Stevens, 1953-1943, John F. Stevens Hall of Fame Committee, 1976. Printed pamphlet, letter and miscellany, 1967-1976 (Box 57, Folder 1)
      - "Maurice H. Thatcher," Encyclopedia of American Biography, " Mimeographed copy, 1967. (Folder 2)
      - "Maurice H. Thatcher," The Panama Canal Review, Mimeographed copy, 1970 august
      - McCullough, David G., "A Man, A Plan, A Canal, Panama!" Printed copy of article on John F. Stevens, undated (Folder 3)
      - Riggs, Arthur Stanley, "Panama Futility," The Catholic World, Mimeographed copy, 1947 january (Folder 4)
      - Sammis, Richard C., "The Panama Canal " Mimeographed typescript done for James R. Grover, Jr., M.C., 1969 (Folder 5)
      - Teller, Edward, Wilson K. Talley, Gary H. Higgins, Gerald W. Johnson, "The Constructive Uses of Nuclear Explosives," Mimeographed copy of book preface, undated (Folder 6)
    - Issues
      - Economic
        - General. Chart, printed and mimeographed copies of articles from serials, 1976-1977 (Folder 7)
        - Agriculture Department, "The Panama Canal and U.S. Farm Trade," Mimeographed copy, 1977 october 17. (Folder 8)
        - Morales, Francisco, "Origins, Development and Effects of the Low Toll Rates Charges of the Panama Canal," Mimeographed copy, 1976 March 26. (Folder 9)
      - Environmental and scientific. Relates primarily to the sea-level canal controversy. Reprints, (including one relating to Dr. Gorgas and yellow fever), meeting agenda, letters, including Reps. Daniel Flood and Leonor Sullivan, printed articles and a mimeographed report by the State Department, Draft Environmental Impact Statement for the New Panama Canal Treaty, which includes correspondence with Rep. Robert J. Lagomarsino, 1966-1977 (Folder 10-12)
      - Inter-American and international relations
        - General. Mimeographed copies of articles from serials, 1971-1979 (Folder 13)
        - Center for Inter-American Relations, "The United States and Latin America: Next Steps," Mimeographed copy, 1976 december 20. (Folder 14)
        - Cox, Robert G., "Choices for Partnership or Bloodshed in Panama," Reprinted from The Americas in a Changing World, 1975. (Folder 15)
        - Kennan, George F., "Latin America," Mimeographed section of chapter from The Cloud of Danger: Current Realities of American Foreign Policy., circa 1975. (Folder 16)
        - Library of Congress, Legislative Reference Service, "Panama-United States Relations Since the Riots of 1959," Mimeographed copy, 1967 august 4. (Folder 17)
        - Noble, G. Bernard, "Inter-American Relations: II," Mimeographed portion of chapter from American Secretaries of State and Their Diplomacy: Christian Herter. Includes notes by William Collier, 1970. (Folder 18)
        - State Department (Folder 19)
          - "Joint Report Presented by the Governments of Panama and the United States of America to the Sixth General Assembly of the Organization of American States," Mimeographed copy. Includes address by Henry A. Kissinger to the meeting, and cover memorandum, 1976 June 9.
          - "U.S. Policy Toward Panama, 1903-Present: Questions of Recognition and Diplomatic Relations and Instances of U.S. Intervention," Historical Studies Division Project No. 1066C, Mimeographed copy, 1974 April 22.
      - Legal. Relates generally to issues which may be more fully discussed in reference to the actual treaty of, 1977
        - General, Mimeographed copies of articles from serials, and report by George F. Mott, "An Overlooked Aspect of the Panama Treaty Debate," relating to the property rights of U.S. citizens in Canal Zone. Includes correspondence between Mott and the State Department on this matter, 1964-1978. (Folder 20-21)
        - Library of Congress, Congressional Reference Service
          - "Disposal by Treaty of United States Property Rights in Panama," Mimeographed copy, 1967 november 14. (Box 58, Folder 1)
          - "Cession of United States Property: Treaty or Act of Congress," Mimeographed copy, 1971 december 30. (Folder 2)
          - "Executive Orders Disposing Canal Zone Functions", Mimeographed copy with notes by William Collier, 1975 July 25. (Folder 3)
          - "Citizenship Status of Panama Canal Zone Residents," Includes cover memorandum. Mimeographed copy, 1976 august 27 (Folder 4)
          - "Arguments Supporting the Role of the House of Representatives in the Disposal of Federal Property in the Canal Zone," Includes cover memorandum. Mimeographed copy, 1977 July 19. (Folder 5)
          - "Treaty Power and Congressional Power in Conflict: Cession of United States Property in the Canal Zone to Panama," Mimeographed copy, 1977 august 4. (Folder 6)
          - "Role of the House of Representatives in the Disposal of U.S. Territory and Property by Treaty," Review of Edwards vs. Carter. Mimeographed copy, 1978 April 10. (Folder 7)
      - Military. Report by the Library of Congress, Congressional Research Service, "The Panama Canal and the Panama Canal Zone: Some of Their Contributions to Strategic Mobility and Logistic Support," Mimeographed copy of a report prepared for, and including a cover memorandum by, Senator Jesse Helms, 1977 december 17. (Folder 8)
    - Chronological reports and documents relating to the construction and diplomatic history of the Panama Canal
      - Undated
        - General. Mimeographed summary of treaty provisions and chapters from an unidentified book relating to the negotiations with Colombia to obtain the Panama concession, 1903 (Folder 9)
        - Harding, Earl, "The Untold Story of Panama". Mimeographed excerpt from book (Folder 10)
        - Humphrey, Chauncey Benton, "The Rebirth of the Panama Canal: An Account of the Revolution at Panama, ". Mimeographed typescript by U.S. Army officer describing his involvement in the revolution., 1902-1903 (Folder 11)
        - Roosevelt, Theodore, "The Panama Blackmail Treaty". Mimeographed chapter from book entitled Fear God and Take Your Own Part (Folder 12)
      - "Treaty Between the U.S. and Great Britain to Facilitate the Construction of a Ship Canal" (Hay-Pauncefote Treaty). Mimeographed copy, 1901. (Folder 13)
      - "Report of the Isthmian Canal Commission". Mimeographed report, 1902 january (Folder 14)
      - "Report of Major W.C. Gorgas, Medical Corps, United States Army". Mimeographed report, 1902 July.
      - "Construction of a Ship Canal to Connect the Waters of the Atlantic and Pacific Oceans". Mimeographed report reprinted in 1938 with treaty revisions noted, 1903. (Folder 15)
      - "Provisional Boundary Agreement". Mimeographed copy, 1904. (Folder 16)
      - "John Hay, Secretary of State, to J.D. de Obaldia, Minister of Panama". U.S. Foreign Relations, p. 612-630. Mimeographed copy, 1904.
      - "Treaty for the Mutual Extradition of Criminals", letter from Theodore Roosevelt to Congress submitting the report of the Board of Consulting Engineers for the Panama Canal, and an excerpt from James Bryce, The American Commonwealth. Mimeographed copies, 1906. (Folder 17)
      - "Boundary Convention". Mimeographed copy, 1914. (Folder 18)
      - "Expropriation Data Expunged by the Washington Censor from Canal Report". Society of the Chagres Yearbook. Mimeographed copy, 1916-1917.
      - "Final Report of the Joint Commission Appointed by the President of the United States and the President of the Republic of Panama". Mimeographed copy, 1920. (Folder 19)
      - "Treaty Between the United States and Colombia: Settlement of Differences". (Thomson-Urrutia treaty). Mimeographed copy, 1922. (Folder 20)
      - (?). Excerpt from mimeographed transcript of discussions leading to Hull-Alfaro Treaty of 1936. (Folder 21)
      - Panama: Eslabon Entre Dos Mundos, printed pamphlet, 1953. (Folder 22)
      - Arthur Wood, "The Construction and the History of the Panama Canal". Original report (term paper), 1954. (Folder 23)
      - "Treaty of Mutual Understanding and Cooperation". Mimeographed copy, 1955. (Folder 24)
      - Charles D. Ameringer, "Bunau-Varilla, Russia, and the Panama Canal". Journal of Inter-American Studies and World Affairs. Mimeographed copy, 1970 July. (Folder 25)
      - Mimeographed summary of Kissinger-Tack Agreement, 1974. (Folder 26)
      - 1977
        - General, Summary of treaties with Panama, Virginia M. Hagen, "Negotiation of New Panama Canal Treaties: Background and Pros and Cons" and Larry Storrs, "Panama Canal Treaties", 1971-1977. (Folder 27)
        - Treaty texts
          - General. Various reprints of the treaty articles, including preliminary document released in Panamanian press (Folder 28)
          - "Message from the President of the United States Transmitting the Panama Canal Treaty and the Treaty Concerning Permanent Neutrality and the Operation of the Panama Canal," Printed copy of report to Congress, 1977 september 17. (Folder 29)
          - "Tratado del Canal de Panama" and "Tratado Concerniente a la Neutralidad Permanent del Canal y al Funcionamiento del Canal de Panama" (Spanish version of above). Mimeographed copies, cover correspondence. Also includes Spanish text of Carter-Torrijos Statement of Understanding (Folder 30)
      - "Protocol of Exchange of Instruments of Ratification". Mimeographed copies (E)(S), 1978 June 16. (Folder 31)
      - "The Panama Canal Act of 1979". Mimeographed copy from State Department, with cover letter, and printed copy, 1979 April. (Folder 32)
  - Interest groups
    - General, Non-Western Hemispheric governments. Letters and clippings, including a letter to Indian Prime Minister Desai, a letter with attachments from the British Foreign Office to Mervyn Pike, M.P., and clippings relating to Communist China and Panama, 1971-1979. (Box 59, Folder 1)
    - Business organizations, Clippings, printed articles, pamphlet, press releases, resolutions, newsletters, speech transcript, charts, letters to Senators Jesse Helms, Frank Lausche, John Stennis and Rep. Daniel Flood. Includes text of a cable sent by Omar Torrijos to President Ford. SEE ALSO: Interest groups/Canal Zonians/Panama Canal Company, 1957-1978. (Folder 2)
    - Canal Zonians
      - General
        - General. Printed and non-printed material. Questionaires, miscellany, and a petition; also includes a printed article by Kenneth D. MacHarg, "A New Canal Zone Treaty,", undated (Folder 3)
        - Clippings
          - Panama American, undated-1976 october (Folder 4-6)
          - Star and Herald, undated-1978 (Folder 7-10)
        - Correspondence
          - General, Includes correspondence with Panama Canal committees, including Dr. Dozer's group, the Emergency Committee to Save the U.S. Canal Zone (ECSCZ); also includes correspondence with the the Canal Zone Central Labor Union, 1967-1978. (Box 60, Folder 1-2)
          - Gilman, James (Panama Canal Pilot). Letters to editors, Congress and the White House, 1975-1978 (Folder 3)
        - Reports
          - Jackley, John L., "A Study of the Impact of a New Panama Canal Treaty on the Non-DoD, U.S. Citizen Canal Zone Resident," Prepared for the U.S. Embassy, Panama. Includes correspondence, 1976. (Folder 4)
          - Pestillo, Peter J., "The Panama Canal Zone Government and the Panama Canal Company Personnel Policies (Folder 5)
        - Speeches and statements
          - General, 1977-1978 (Folder 6)
          - U.S. Civic Councils. Includes meeting reports and position papers, 1975-1977 (Folder 7)
      - Canal Zone Police Union
        - General, Newsletters, memoranda and letters, 1971-1977. (Folder 8)
        - Litigation against Panama Canal Company. Relates to labor problems which developed after the riots, 1964
          - General, Notes, clippings, legal documents, 1964-1974. (Folder 9)
          - Correspondence, 1958-1969 (Folder 10)
      - Panama Canal Company
        - General
          - Non-printed material, Schedules, maps, letters, charts, miscellany, 1937-1948. (Folder 11)
          - Printed material
            - General. Pamphlets and flyers, 1962-1977 (Folder 12-13)
            - Daily Digest. Newsletter, 1967-1976 (Box 61, Folder 1-4)
            - Panama Canal Review. Serial issues, 1967-1975 (Folder 5-6)
            - Panama Canal Spillway. Newsletter, 1969-1977 (Folder 7)
        - Correspondence. Includes ECSCZ, 1966-1977 (Folder 8)
        - Reports (Folder 9)
          - Untitled. Memorandum and report relating to port facilities for Panamanian sugar and molasses storage. Includes letters from Panamian officials, Mimeographed copy, 1976 July 31.
          - President's Report to Board of Directors, Fiscal Year, Printed copy, 1968.
          - "Proposal to Increase Tolls," Mimeographed copy, 1973 december 15.
          - Annual Report, Printed copy, 1969.
          - "Report of Operational Water Board," Includes cover letter. Mimeographed copy, 1972.
        - Speeches and statements. Leber, W.P. (Gov.), 1970 May 19 (Folder 10)
      - Panama Canal Zone Non-profit Public Information Corporation (PCZNPIC)
        - General
          - Non-printed material, Form letters, flyers, petitions, press releases, 1968-1978. (Folder 11)
          - Printed material, Clippings relating to the group, 1976. (Box 62, Folder 1)
        - Correspondence
          - General. Includes letters to Cyrus Vance and Nelson Rockefeller (Folder 2)
          - Emergency Committee to Save the U.S. Canal Zone (ECSCZ), and other Panama Canal groups, 1975-1978 (Folder 3-5)
          - U.S. Congress General, Flood, Daniel, 1975-1977 1971-1975 (Folder 6)
        - Legal materials. Relates to efforts to block the negotiations and resultant treaties by legal methods. Notes and fragements, legal documents, and correspondence, 1975-1978 (Folder 7)
        - Letters to editors, 1976-1977 (Folder 8)
        - Miscellany. Incorporation and administrative materials, 1975-1977 (Folder 9)
        - Speeches and statements, 1975-1977 (Folder 10)
    - Citizens groups - General
      - General. Includes unique materials or isolated groups or individuals.
        - General (Folder 11-12)
          - Non-printed material, Correspondence, form letters, petitions, newsletters, campaign material, flyers, promotional material, program agenda, memoranda, verses. Includes anonymous, undated report entitled "Financial Benefits to Panama from the Presence of the United States in the Canal Zone". Also includes various documents relating to Communist influence in Panama, 1975-1979.
          - Printed material, Form letters, advertisements, pamphlets, flyers, clippings, serial issues, and printed articles, 1964-1978. (Box 63, Folder 1-4)
        - Correspondence
          - General, 1967-1978 (Folder 5)
          - Executive, 1974-1978 (Folder 6)
          - Military organizations, 1975 (Folder 7)
          - U.S. Congress, Arranged alphabetically by addressee, 1966-1977. (Folder 8)
        - Letters to the editor, Includes letters from John Wayne, Spruille Braden, Paul Chiera, 1968-1978. (Folder 9)
        - Media transcripts
          - Broadcasts
            - General, Includes CBS "60 Minutes" and a broadcast by Phyllis Schlafly, 1967-1977. (Folder 10)
            - Manion (Dean) Forum, 1965-1978 (Folder 11)
          - Syndicated columns
            - General, 1967-1978 (Folder 12)
            - Allen, Robert S., 1974-1978 (Box 64, Folder 1-2)
        - Miscellany. Print (illustration) and bumper stickers, circa 1978 (Folder 3)
        - Newsletters
          - General, Miscellaneous single issues, 1967-1979. (Folder 4)
          - America's Future, 1975-1979 (Folder 5)
          - Conservative Viewpoint, 1967-1976 (Folder 6)
          - Dan Smoot Report, 1966-1967
          - Don Bell Reports, 1976-1978
          - Hemisphere Hotline Report, 1975-1977 (Folder 7)
          - Herald of Freedom, 1974-1978
          - Intelligence Digest, 1976-1979
          - Mindszenty Report, 1976-1977
          - (New) Right Report, 1976-1978 (Folder 8)
          - Phyllis Schlafly Report, 1967-1978
          - Tactics, 1975-1978 (Folder 9)
          - Washington Observer, 1967 (Folder 10)
        - Press releases, 1967-1978 (Folder 11)
        - Reports, Includes a mimeographed copy of George Fox Mott, "The Panama Canal: Today's Decision--Tomorrow's Security," 1977 and a printed pamphlet by James P. Lucier, Panama Canal: Focus on Power Politics, 1977-1978. 1974 (Folder 12)
        - Resolutions. General (Folder 13)
        - Statements and speeches
          - General (Folder 14)
          - Braden, Spruille. Mimeographed speech transcript, 1977 Feb 28 (Folder 15)
          - Thomson, Meldrim, Jr. Mimeographed and printed speech transcripts, 1977 June-september (Folder 16)
      - Accuracy in Media, Letters to the editor, form letter, newsletter, columns, 1976-1979. (Folder 17)
      - American Cause, Inc., Newsletters and flyers, 1975-1978. (Folder 18)
      - American Coalition of Patriotic Societies, Inc., Resolutions, 1966-1977. (Folder 19)
      - American Conservative Union, Form letters, correspondence, memoranda, pamphlet, press release, serial issues (Battleline), 1967-1978. (Folder 20)
      - American Council for World Freedom (Task Force on the Panama Canal), Flyer, program agenda, press releases, newsletter, and a report entitled "Who and What is Panama's Dictator, General Omar Torrijos," circa 1977, 1975-1979. (Folder 21)
      - Americanism Educational League, Pamphlets and statement written by Spruille Braden, correspondence, newsletters, undated (Folder 22)
      - American Security Council, Conference memorandum, form letters, newsletters, correspondence with Daniel Flood which includes poll results, 1967-1969. (Box 65, Folder 1)
      - Committee of Tax-weary and Concerned Americans, Flyers, form letters, newspaper advertisements, 1978-1979. (Folder 2)
      - Committee on Pan-American Policy (John Birch Society), 1959-1979.
        - General. Form letters, newsletters (Pan American Headlines), petition, correspondence with Dr. Dozer (Folder 3)
        - Printed material. Pamphlets and flyers. Includes Earl Harding, "The Untold Story of Panama." Reprint, 1959 (Folder 4)
      - Committee to Restore the Constitution, Inc., Newsletters, 1972-1977. (Folder 5)
      - Conservative Caucus, Form letters, flyers, newsletters, letter, 1979. (Folder 6)
      - Council for Inter-American Security, 1976-1980